<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.14 -->
<document source="C:\Users\cande\aide\aide_design_specs\doc_files\Filtration\Filt_Purpose_and_Description.rst">
    <target refid="title-filt-proposito-y-descripcion"></target>
    <section ids="proposito-y-descripcion title-filt-proposito-y-descripcion" names="prop贸sito\ y\ descripci贸n purpose\ and\ description title_filt_prop贸sito_y_descripci贸n">
        <title>Purpose and Description</title>
        <paragraph>As a final process in solids removal, this design uses rapid sand filtration in the form of the FRAMCA (Multi-Layer Rapid Sand Filter) of AguaClara. Rapid filtration further lowers the turbidity of the water after sedimentation, and removes harmful microorganisms that are resistant to chlorine. The process involves passing the sedimented water through a bed of sand, with sufficient speed that the particles can enter the sand and not wash off the surface.</paragraph>
        <target refid="figure-filt-diagram-1"></target>
        <figure align="center" ids="id1 figure-filt-diagram-1" names="figure_filt_diagram_1">
            <image candidates="{'*': 'Filtration\\Images/filt_diagram_1.png'}" uri="Filtration\Images/filt_diagram_1.png" width="750px"></image>
            <caption>Water passes through a fast sand filter faster than a slow filter. Therefore, the sediment goes deep into the entire sand bed instead of being washed to the surface.</caption>
        </figure>
        <paragraph>Instead of passing water in only one direction, the FRAMCA injects the water at four different levels and collects it from three points in between, so that the flow is divided among six layers of sand (<number_reference internal="True" refid="figure-filt-backwash" title="Fig. %s"><inline classes="std std-numref">Fig. 37</inline></number_reference>). This configuration allows backwashing without pumps. The backwash cycle requires approximately six times the water velocity of the filtration cycle to fluidize the sand and purge the accumulated sediment. In many conventional hydraulic sand filter systems (operating by gravity only, with no electrical power) a battery of parallel filters is used so that the flows from six active filters in the filtration cycle can be combined to backwash one at a time.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>The AguaClara FRAMCA, on the other hand, effectively puts the filters of this battery on top of each other, in six horizontal layers, thus preserving the flat area. In this way, the entire flow rate that is normally divided among the inputs of the six layers in the filtration cycle is concentrated in a single lower input in the backwash cycle (<number_reference internal="True" refid="figure-filt-backwash" title="Fig. %s"><inline classes="std std-numref">Fig. 37</inline></number_reference>).</paragraph>
        <target refid="figure-filt-backwash"></target>
        <figure align="center" ids="id2 figure-filt-backwash" names="figure_filt_backwash">
            <image candidates="{'*': 'Filtration\\Images/filt_backwash.png'}" uri="Filtration\Images/filt_backwash.png" width="600px"></image>
            <caption>Concept of the water paths in the FRAMCA sand during the filtration cycle and the backwash cycle.</caption>
        </figure>
        <paragraph>Compared to a conventional fast filter, the FRAMCA:</paragraph>
        <block_quote>
            <bullet_list bullet="-">
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>It does not require pumps for backwashing.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>It takes up six times less area to treat the same flow.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>It uses less water for backwashing.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>It is backwashed with sedimentary water, not filtered water. This way you can use the same water that is entering the filter to backwash it. There is no need for additional tanks to store filtered water.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>Water enters and exits through manifolds into the sand bed.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
                <list_item>
                    <paragraph>It filters the water through a thinner layer of sand.</paragraph>
                </list_item>
            </bullet_list>
        </block_quote>
        <target refid="figure-framca"></target>
        <figure align="center" ids="id3 figure-framca" names="figure_framca">
            <image candidates="{'*': 'Filtration\\Images/framca.png'}" uri="Filtration\Images/framca.png" width="500px"></image>
            <caption>The FRAMCA, because of its six-layer configuration, achieves the same results as six conventional filters.</caption>
        </figure>
        <target refid="figure-framca-cycles"></target>
        <figure align="center" ids="id4 figure-framca-cycles" names="figure_framca_cycles">
            <image candidates="{'*': 'Filtration\\Images/framca_cycles.png'}" uri="Filtration\Images/framca_cycles.png" width="800px"></image>
            <caption>The FRAMCA of AguaClara in the two main modes of operation: the filtration cycle and the backwash cycle.</caption>
        </figure>
        <target refid="figure-framca-transparent"></target>
        <figure align="center" ids="id5 figure-framca-transparent" names="figure_framca_transparent">
            <image candidates="{'*': 'Filtration\\Images/framca_transparent.png'}" uri="Filtration\Images/framca_transparent.png" width="800px"></image>
            <caption>Isometric view of the FRAMCA and the cleaning channel with transparent walls.</caption>
        </figure>
    </section>
</document>
