<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.14 -->
<document source="C:\Users\cande\aide\aide_design_specs\doc_files\Introduction\Treatment_Process.rst">
    <target refid="title-procesos-de-tratamiento"></target>
    <section ids="procesos-de-tratamiento title-procesos-de-tratamiento" names="procesos\ de\ tratamiento treatment\ processes title_procesos_de_tratamiento">
        <title>Treatment Processes</title>
        <paragraph>The plants produce clean and safe water, after the removal of sediments and pathogens. AguaClara technology uses the unitary processes of coagulation, flocculation, sedimentation, rapid sand filtration, and chlorine disinfection (<literal classes="xref std std-numref">figure_process</literal>).</paragraph>
        <target refid="figure-process"></target>
        <figure align="center" ids="id1 figure-process" names="figure_process">
            <image candidates="{'*': 'Introduction\\Images/process.png'}" uri="Introduction\Images/process.png" width="650px"></image>
            <caption>The treatment processes used in the AguaClara plant.</caption>
        </figure>
        <target refid="heading-el-tanque-de-entrada"></target>
        <section ids="el-tanque-de-entrada heading-el-tanque-de-entrada" names="el\ tanque\ de\ entrada the\ entrance\ tank heading_el_tanque_de_entrada">
            <title>The entrance tank</title>
            <paragraph>The process starts in the <strong>entrance tank</strong>, which serves both to remove the coarse material from the water and to measure the water flow for the dosing of the chemicals. The entrance tank functions as a sedimentation tank in which coarse particles fall to the bottom of the tank by gravity. Due to the special design of the outlet, the water level in the tank varies in proportion to the water flow in the plant. This water level is connected to the semi-automatic chemical dosing system, so that doses of coagulant and chlorine are maintained even when the water flow in the plant changes. By means of the chemical dosing system, a coagulant is applied at the outlet of the entrance tank, which binds with the raw water in the <strong>quick mix</strong>.</paragraph>
            <target refid="heading-mezcla-rapida"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="mezcla-rapida heading-mezcla-rapida" names="mezcla\ rápida rapid\ mixing heading_mezcla_rápida">
            <title>Rapid mixing</title>
            <paragraph>Rapid mixing distributes the coagulant evenly in the raw water. It is simply a hole, narrower than the tube that transmits the water. When the flow expands again after the orifice, the expansion turbulence is sufficient to distribute the chemical. With the mixture of the chemical with the water the process of <strong>coagulation</strong> begins, in which the fine suspended particles, called colloids, are covered with nanoparticles of the coagulant. In effect, the coagulant’s nanoparticles act as a glue so that when the particles, whether they are clay or pathogenic, collide with each other they no longer repel each other, but remain stuck together.</paragraph>
            <target refid="heading-floculacion"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="floculacion heading-floculacion" names="floculación flocculation heading_floculación">
            <title>Flocculation</title>
            <paragraph>Then the water-coagulant mixture enters the <strong>flocculator</strong>, a series of channels with baffles that direct the water flow. The smooth mixture in the flocculator flow promotes collisions between particles, and these get stuck by the effect of the coagulant’s nanoparticles. During this process, which is called flocculation, the particles grow, forming agglomerations (<strong>flocs</strong>). In the end they have reached a visible size, and have a high enough terminal velocity to be eliminated in the next process, the <strong>sedimentation</strong>.</paragraph>
            <target refid="heading-sedimentacion"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="sedimentacion heading-sedimentacion" names="sedimentación sedimentation heading_sedimentación">
            <title>Sedimentation</title>
            <paragraph>The <strong>sedimentation tank</strong> removes most of the suspended particles using three processes. It starts with the sludge blanket which is a fluidized bed of flocs that work as a filter to trap small particles. The excess flocs pass through a chute to accumulate in a hopper where they can be concentrated and go out to the drainage channel. Above the sludge blanket there is a series of inclined sheets. These sedimentation plates allow the capture of particles with a low terminal velocity. The sedimented water exits the tank above the plates through a perforated tube.</paragraph>
            <target refid="heading-manto-de-lodos"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="manto-de-lodos heading-manto-de-lodos" names="manto\ de\ lodos sludge\ blanket heading_manto_de_lodos">
            <title>Sludge blanket</title>
            <paragraph>At the bottom, where the flocculated water enters, the sedimentation tanks have facilities that maintain a <strong>sludge blanket</strong>, a dense bed of suspended flocs. Water entering the tank has to first pass through the sludge blanket before reaching the plates above. The suspended flocs in effect serve as a filter to capture the finer particles, which would otherwise pass the sedimentation process. Jets of water entering the tank lift the sludge that has settled, keeping it in suspension.</paragraph>
            <target refid="heading-filtracion-con-arena"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="filtracion-con-arena heading-filtracion-con-arena" names="filtración\ con\ arena sand\ filtration heading_filtración_con_arena">
            <title>Sand filtration</title>
            <paragraph>After sedimentation, the plant uses the <strong>rapid sand filtration</strong> in the form of the FRAMCA (Fast Multi-Layer Open Sand Filter) of AguaClara. The process consists of passing the sedimented water through a bed of sand where the suspended particles are captured. It serves to further lower the turbidity and to capture any parasites that remain after sedimentation. The filter needs to be backwashed regularly to remove the sediment accumulated in the sand. The AguaClara FRAMCA is designed to perform the backwash cycle without any pump. The layered design reduces the area needed for construction compared to other rapid filter systems and reduces the amount of water used for backwashing.</paragraph>
            <target refid="heading-desinfeccion"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="desinfeccion heading-desinfeccion" names="desinfección disinfection heading_desinfección">
            <title>Disinfection</title>
            <paragraph>Before distribution, the water is <strong>disinfected</strong> with chlorine to inactivate any remaining harmful microorganisms. The calcium hypochlorite solution is dosed using the same system that is used for the coagulant, located in the entrance tank, and transmitted through a PVC pipe to the plant outlet. This last step is carried out after the removal of the suspended solids because disinfection does not work with dirty water due to the intervention of particles and organic materials. Chlorine also serves to protect against contamination in the distribution network and in houses. Therefore, the dose must be sufficient to maintain a residue in the last water system connection.</paragraph>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
