<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.14 -->
<document source="C:\Users\cande\aide\aide_design_specs\doc_files\Sedimentation\Floc_Blanket.rst">
    <target refid="title-el-manto-de-lodos"></target>
    <section ids="el-manto-de-lodos title-el-manto-de-lodos" names="el\ manto\ de\ lodos the\ sludge\ blanket title_el_manto_de_lodos">
        <title>The Sludge Blanket</title>
        <paragraph>AguaClara’s sedimentation tanks are designed with the goal of achieving another physical phenomenon at the bottom of the tank called the sludge blanket. This feature of the tank can improve the quality of the water it produces. The sludge blanket is a dense bed of flocs suspended in the water, the product of the accumulation of solids captured over time. The floc bed functions as a pre-filter. The particles that enter and pass through the sludge blanket collide with the already suspended flocs, and thus the smaller particles, which may not be captured without the presence of the sludge blanket, remain at the bottom of the tank. The inclined plates prevent the smaller solids from escaping from the top.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>The laboratory investigations have shown that a well-defined surface is established between the sludge blanket and the clearer water coming from above. The floc suspension and the water above it behave as two different fluids. The surface level between the sludge blanket and the clean water is maintained by the <strong>floc chute</strong>, a wall over which the flocs fall into a hopper when they reach the top of the chute. The flocs in the bed are kept suspended by the inlet jets at the bottom of the tank.</paragraph>
        <target refid="figure-sed-tank-front"></target>
        <figure align="center" ids="id1 figure-sed-tank-front" names="figure_sed_tank_front">
            <image candidates="{'*': 'Sedimentation\\Images/sed_tank_front.png'}" uri="Sedimentation\Images/sed_tank_front.png" width="500px"></image>
            <caption>Front view of the experimental sedimentation tank at Cornell University’s AguaClara Laboratory.</caption>
        </figure>
    </section>
</document>
