<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.14 -->
<document source="C:\Users\cande\aide\aide_design_specs\doc_files\Flocculation\Floc_Design_Concepts.rst">
    <target refid="title-conceptos-de-diseno-del-floculador"></target>
    <section ids="conceptos-de-diseno-del-floculador title-conceptos-de-diseno-del-floculador" names="conceptos\ de\ diseño\ del\ floculador flocculator\ design\ concepts title_conceptos_de_diseño_del_floculador">
        <title>Flocculator Design Concepts</title>
        <target refid="heading-el-potencial-de-colisiones-y-el-rendimiento-del-floculador"></target>
        <section ids="el-potencial-de-colisiones-y-el-rendimiento-del-floculador heading-el-potencial-de-colisiones-y-el-rendimiento-del-floculador" names="el\ potencial\ de\ colisiones\ y\ el\ rendimiento\ del\ floculador collision\ potential\ and\ flocculator\ performance heading_el_potencial_de_colisiones_y\ el_rendimiento_del_floculador">
            <title>Collision potential and flocculator performance</title>
            <paragraph>We start with potential energy that can be seen by the difference in level between upstream and downstream in the flocculator. This potential energy converts to kinetic energy in the downstream flow contractions of changes of direction or restrictions.  Then the jets coming out of the contractions break up into eddies. The rate of converting mechanical energy into eddies and then heat is</paragraph>
            <target refid="equation-edr-of-headloss"></target>
            <math_block docname="Flocculation/Floc_Design_Concepts" ids="equation-edr-of-headloss" label="EDR_of_headloss" nowrap="False" number="1" xml:space="preserve">\bar \varepsilon \theta = g h_L</math_block>
            <paragraph>where <math>\bar \varepsilon \theta</math> is the mechanical energy that is converted to heat in the flocculator and <math>g h_L</math> is the potential energy that is lost to heat in the flocculator. In the process of converting the energy from the eddies to heat the water is deformed. The rate of deformation of the fluid is the velocity gradient, G. The rate of energy dissipation is related to the velocity gradient by the formula:</paragraph>
            <target refid="equation-edr-of-g"></target>
            <math_block docname="Flocculation/Floc_Design_Concepts" ids="equation-edr-of-g" label="EDR_of_G" nowrap="False" number="2" xml:space="preserve">\bar \varepsilon=\nu G_{CS}^2</math_block>
            <paragraph>Where <math>\nu</math> is the kinematic viscosity of water and <math>G_{CS}</math> is the defined speed gradient of Camp and Stein (1955)</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In order to reduce the concentration of primary particles that have not combined with other particles we have to give a certain amount of water deformation. The amount of water deformation is what gives the collisions between the particles and that’s why the potential of collisions is the product of the retention time, <math>\theta</math> and the velocity gradient, <math>G_{CS}</math>, of Camp and Stein (1955).</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The AguaClara flocculation model gives the form of the relationship between the collision potential and the concentration of non-flocculated primary particles.</paragraph>
            <target refid="equation-gtlam"></target>
            <math_block docname="Flocculation/Floc_Design_Concepts" ids="equation-gtlam" label="Gtlam" nowrap="False" number="3" xml:space="preserve">      G_{CS}\theta = \frac{3}{2}\frac{{\left( {{\bar \Lambda ^2} - \bar \Lambda_0^2} \right)}}{{k\pi\bar{\alpha} \bar{d}_P^2}}</math_block>
            <paragraph>where <math>\bar \Lambda_0</math> is the distance between prime particles in raw water, <math>\bar \Lambda</math> is the distance between prime particles coming out of the flocculator, <math>\bar{\alpha}</math> is the probability that the collision point between two prime particles is a nano coagulant particle, <math>\bar{d}_P</math> is the diameter of the prime particles, and <math>k</math> represents the fraction of prime particles that convert to a flocculum with a terminal settling velocity greater than the capture velocity of the settling plates. Equation <reference internal="True" refid="equation-gtlam">(16)</reference> shows that in order to achieve a low concentration of first particles at the flocculator outlet, a high <math>\bar \Lambda</math>, it is necessary to design a flocculator with high collision strength, <math>G_{CS}\theta</math>.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The collision potential, <math>G_{CS}\theta</math>, is a property of the flocculator itself, independent of the characteristics of the raw water, the coagulant dosage, and the design of the sedimentation process. The flocculator of the AguaClara plant is designed with a minimum collision potential of <problematic ids="id4" refid="id3">|Gt.FlocBod|</problematic>, which has been successful in plants that have a sludge blanket.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>However, unlike some conventional methodologies, no raw water characteristics are considered in the design of the AguaClara flocculator other than the general need for the flocculation, sludge blanket, and sedimentation processes to remove suspended solids. That is, the design is independent of the results of jug tests or other preliminary analysis because the jug test cannot capture the key process in the sludge blanket. The only predictive model factors considered in the design are those related to the potential for collisions and the effect of water viscosity. Rather than knowing the characteristics of the raw water, the goal is to design a flocculator that can effectively flocculate any suspension with sufficient coagulant coverage. That is why the design tool does not ask for any user input related to treatability testing. Raw water only enters the design of coagulant and chlorine dosers where the demand for these two chemicals at the most critical times determines the maximum dosage.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The design of AguaClara has been formulated to be independent of raw water for two main reasons:</paragraph>
            <block_quote>
                <enumerated_list enumtype="arabic" prefix="" suffix=".">
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Pitcher test results can be useful in determining coagulation efficiency by varying the coagulant dose, but they are not normally applied to full-scale flocculation because of fundamental process differences, such as the large variety of local speed gradients in shaker reactors and the lack of the sludge blanket process in the pitcher test.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>The characteristics of raw water always vary over time, and in many cases it is difficult to obtain a representative set of data within the time and budget available for the study and design of the plant. One of AguaClara’s main goals is to provide effective solutions that reduce costs and time as much as possible in order to serve the maximum number of people.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                </enumerated_list>
            </block_quote>
            <paragraph>The design takes into account the filtration process that takes place in the sludge blanket in the sedimentation tank. The sludge blanket is a suspension of flocs that is held at the bottom of the settling tank and provides the opportunity for collisions between particles caused by differential settling. Because of the work that the sludge blanket does, AguaClara plants achieve low levels of turbidity in the decanted water even though they use a flocculator with low potential for collisions.</paragraph>
            <target refid="heading-eficiencia-del-floculador"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="eficiencia-del-floculador heading-eficiencia-del-floculador" names="eficiencia\ del\ floculador flocculator\ efficiency heading_eficiencia\ del\ floculador">
            <title>Flocculator efficiency</title>
            <paragraph>The efficiency of potential energy conversion to water deformation depends on the uniformity of the energy dissipation rate. If there are spaces with high turbulence and other spaces with low turbulence the total deformation of the fluid will be much lower than if it had achieved a uniform turbulence given the same energy. Mechanized flocculators and also many conventional hydraulic flocculators make it necessary to consider the impact of non-uniform turbulence space. For example, the rate of energy dissipation is much higher than the average rate behind the tilted propeller blades. Therefore it does not make sense to compare the collision potential calculated by <math>G_{CS}\theta</math> between mechanized flocculators and flocculators that are designed to optimize the uniformity of the energy dissipation rate.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The jet expansion caused by turning around a deflector takes up only part of the space between the following plates (<number_reference internal="True" refid="figure-floc-energy-dissipation" title="Fig. %s"><inline classes="std std-numref">Fig. 24</inline></number_reference>). This expansion is where the turbulence that ultimately causes the deformation of the water and the relative velocities that bring the suspended particles together is found. Within the jet there are regions of high energy dissipation, which indicates violent turbulence and high relative velocities, and there are also areas of softer turbulence. Similarly, there are regions of the flow that contribute very little to flocculation because they are outside the expansion of the jet. If the rate of energy dissipation were uniform it would be an ideal flocculator, with uniform turbulence and the entire volume contributing equally to particle bonding.</paragraph>
            <target refid="figure-floc-energy-dissipation"></target>
            <figure align="center" ids="id1 figure-floc-energy-dissipation" names="figure_floc_energy_dissipation">
                <image candidates="{'*': 'Flocculation\\Images/floc_energy_dissipation.png'}" uri="Flocculation\Images/floc_energy_dissipation.png" width="400px"></image>
                <caption>Distribution of the rate of energy dissipation in a flocculator according to CFD analysis.</caption>
            </figure>
            <paragraph>The geometry of the baffles determines the uniformity of the energy dissipation. In particular, the radius of the jet expansion length to the baffle gap (H/S) is directly related to the expansion uniformity. In other words, this radius determines the efficiency of the flocculator in terms of the percentage of the space that contributes to particle bonding. If the space for expansion is very long compared to the deflector separation, the jet expansion is completed in the first part of the available space and a large part of the flocculator volume is wasted (<number_reference internal="True" refid="figure-energy-dissipation-uniformity" title="Fig. %s"><inline classes="std std-numref">Fig. 25</inline></number_reference>).</paragraph>
            <target refid="figure-energy-dissipation-uniformity"></target>
            <figure align="center" ids="id2 figure-energy-dissipation-uniformity" names="figure_energy_dissipation_uniformity">
                <image candidates="{'*': 'Flocculation\\Images/energy_dissipation_uniformity.png'}" uri="Flocculation\Images/energy_dissipation_uniformity.png" width="200px"></image>
                <caption>The radius from the length of the expansion to the deflector gap (H/S) determines the spatial uniformity of the energy dissipation.</caption>
            </figure>
            <paragraph>According to a series of CFD analyses, the optimal range of the H/S ratio is between <problematic ids="id6" refid="id5">|Pi.HSMin|</problematic> and <problematic ids="id8" refid="id7">|Pi.HSTransition|</problematic>. Here the radius <math>\frac{\varepsilon_{max}}{\bar \varepsilon}</math> is equal to 2. Above the optimal range the turbulence uniformity deteriorates.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Construction restrictions for lower flows require an H/S radius that is too high for efficient design. The minimum height of the channels was determined by the height of the adjacent settling tank, and the minimum width of the channels was determined by the space required during construction. Because of the channel width, the separation between baffles had to be smaller to achieve the required velocity gradient. For simplicity of manufacture, there was only one expansion between every two blades. Especially for smaller flows, the result of these restrictions was an H/S radius well above the optimum range. It was necessary to compensate with a larger flocculator to meet the target collision potential.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The flocculator is now designed with additional obstacles between the sheets that cause additional expansions. In this way the length of the space after each expansion is reduced and the H/S radius can be kept within the optimum range. The obstacles are two pieces of PVC pipe between which the water has to flow, causing a contraction equal to the contraction that occurs after the turn around a baffle.</paragraph>
            <target refid="heading-la-tasa-maxima-de-la-disipacion-de-energia"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="la-tasa-maxima-de-la-disipacion-de-energia heading-la-tasa-maxima-de-la-disipacion-de-energia" names="la\ tasa\ máxima\ de\ la\ disipación\ de\ energía the\ maximum\ rate\ of\ energy\ dissipation heading_la_tasa_máxima_de_la_disipación_de_energía">
            <title>The maximum rate of energy dissipation</title>
            <paragraph>It is not the maximum size of the flocs that really determines the quality of the settled water, but the number of primary particles that have not flocculated by the end of the process. For example, larger flocs, if split in two by the shear force of the flow, will always be captured in the sedimentation tank, since the capture rate is much less than the sedimentation rate of these flocs. The particles that constitute the turbidity of the effluent are much smaller, and it is likely that their origin is due to the lack of coverage of the coagulant, not to the high dissipation of energy.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>In several laboratory simulations where the retention time and velocity gradient in a laminar flow flocculator were varied, preliminary data suggest that a reduction in retention time can be compensated for by an increase in the velocity gradient (thus keeping the potential for collisions constant) to produce the same result with respect to settled water quality. It is true that increasing the velocity gradient limits the maximum floc size. Thus, this result suggests that the maximum floc size is not critical to the performance of the treatment system especially when it includes a sludge blanket where flocs continue to grow.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Ultimately, the floccules will be subjected to an energy dissipation rate of <problematic ids="id10" refid="id9">|ED.SedInlet|</problematic> at the inlet to the settling tank to cause <problematic ids="id12" refid="id11">|HL.SedDiffuser|</problematic> of head loss to maintain uniform flow distribution throughout the manifold and to suspend the floccules that have settled to the bottom of the settling tank. Data from the laboratory simulation that was done to test this design suggests that the sediment water quality is not diminished until the rate of energy dissipation at the tank inlet exceeds 300 mW/kg which is equivalent to a velocity gradient of 550 Hz. Since the maximum floc size will be limited by the sedimentation tank inlet, it is clear that it is not necessary to design a flocculator to produce large flocs that will later break up.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Since the velocity gradient at the inlet of the sedimentation tank is higher than the velocity gradient used in the flocculator it is not necessary or convenient to use a series of declining gradients in the flocculator. It is simpler and more efficient to use a single gradient for the entire flocculator to obtain the maximum potential for collisions using the least amount of energy.</paragraph>
            <target refid="heading-las-dimensiones-del-floculador-y-la-gradiente-de-velocidad"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="las-dimensiones-del-floculador-y-la-gradiente-de-velocidad heading-las-dimensiones-del-floculador-y-la-gradiente-de-velocidad" names="las\ dimensiones\ del\ floculador\ y\ la\ gradiente\ de\ velocidad flocculator\ dimensions\ and\ speed\ gradient heading_las_dimensiones_del_floculador_y_la_gradiente_de_velocidad">
            <title>Flocculator dimensions and speed gradient</title>
            <paragraph>The design begins with the potential for collisions, <problematic ids="id14" refid="id13">|Gt.FlocBod|</problematic>, and the available pressure drop for the flocculator, <problematic ids="id16" refid="id15">|HL.FlocBod|</problematic>. With the combination of equation <reference internal="True" refid="equation-edr-of-g">(15)</reference> and equation <reference internal="True" refid="equation-edr-of-headloss">(14)</reference> a relation between pressure drop and speed gradient is obtained.</paragraph>
            <target refid="equation-gofhltheta"></target>
            <math_block docname="Flocculation/Floc_Design_Concepts" ids="equation-gofhltheta" label="GofHLtheta" nowrap="False" number="4" xml:space="preserve">G_{CS} = \sqrt{\frac{g h_L}{\nu \theta}}</math_block>
            <paragraph><math>G_{CS}</math> and <math>\theta</math> are still unknown but we know the value of <math>G_{CS}\theta</math> and so we can remove <math>\theta</math> from the equation <reference internal="True" refid="equation-gofhltheta">(17)</reference></paragraph>
            <target refid="equation-gofhl"></target>
            <math_block docname="Flocculation/Floc_Design_Concepts" ids="equation-gofhl" label="GofHL" nowrap="False" number="5" xml:space="preserve">G_{CS} = \frac{g h_{L_{floc}}}{\nu (G_{CS} \theta)}</math_block>
            <paragraph>The value of <math>G_{CS}</math> is <problematic ids="id18" refid="id17">|G.Floc|</problematic> and you can combine that with the collision potential <math>G_{CS}\theta</math> to get the value of the flocculator retention time. The volume of the flocculator without taking into account the unevenness of the water would be</paragraph>
            <target refid="equation-floc-volume"></target>
            <math_block docname="Flocculation/Floc_Design_Concepts" ids="equation-floc-volume" label="Floc_volume" nowrap="False" number="6" xml:space="preserve">\rlap{--} V_{floc} = \frac{\theta}{Q}</math_block>
            <paragraph>To calculate the space between plates we use the value of <math>G_{CS}</math>, <problematic ids="id20" refid="id19">|G.Floc|</problematic>, and consider the design of an expansion. For the next steps, we consider the flow through an expansion in the flocculator. The distance between expansions, <math>H_e</math>, has a value of <problematic ids="id22" refid="id21">|He.Floc|</problematic>. The retention time for an expansion is <math>\theta_e</math> and the pressure drop for an expansion is <math>h_{L_{e}}</math>.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>We begin by equalizing the rate of energy dissipation, <math>\bar \varepsilon = \nu G_{CS}^2</math> and <math>\bar \varepsilon = \frac{g h_{L_e}}{\theta_e}</math> to obtain an equation based on <math>G_{CS}</math>.</paragraph>
            <target refid="equation-g-of-hl"></target>
            <math_block docname="Flocculation/Floc_Design_Concepts" ids="equation-g-of-hl" label="G_of_HL" nowrap="False" number="7" xml:space="preserve"> \nu G_{CS}^2 = \frac{g h_{L_e}}{\theta_e}</math_block>
            <paragraph>We can use three relationships to calculate the space between plates using equation <reference internal="True" refid="equation-g-of-hl">(20)</reference>.</paragraph>
            <block_quote>
                <enumerated_list enumtype="arabic" prefix="" suffix=".">
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Minor losses: <math>h_{L_{e}} = K \frac{\bar v^2}{2g}</math></paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Retention time in an expansion: <math>\theta_e = \frac{H_e}{\bar v}</math></paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Average speed in the flocculator: <math>\bar v = \frac{Q}{WS}</math></paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                </enumerated_list>
            </block_quote>
            <paragraph>Substituting the three relations in equation <reference internal="True" refid="equation-g-of-hl">(20)</reference> starting with the elimination of the pressure drop.</paragraph>
            <target refid="equation-g-of-ktheta"></target>
            <math_block docname="Flocculation/Floc_Design_Concepts" ids="equation-g-of-ktheta" label="G_of_Ktheta" nowrap="False" number="8" xml:space="preserve">\nu G_{CS}^2 = K \frac{\bar v^2}{2 \theta_e}</math_block>
            <paragraph>Eliminate retention time.</paragraph>
            <target refid="equation-g-of-khev"></target>
            <math_block docname="Flocculation/Floc_Design_Concepts" ids="equation-g-of-khev" label="G_of_KHev" nowrap="False" number="9" xml:space="preserve">\nu G_{CS}^2 = K \frac{\bar v^3}{2 H_e}</math_block>
            <paragraph>Eliminate speed.</paragraph>
            <target refid="equation-g-of-kheq"></target>
            <math_block docname="Flocculation/Floc_Design_Concepts" ids="equation-g-of-kheq" label="G_of_KHeQ" nowrap="False" number="10" xml:space="preserve">\nu G_{CS}^2 = \frac{K}{2 H_e} \left( \frac{Q}{WS} \right)^3</math_block>
            <paragraph>Given the width of the channel, <problematic ids="id24" refid="id23">|W.FlocChannel|</problematic>, in this design we can calculate the space between plates.</paragraph>
            <target refid="equation-s-of-kheq"></target>
            <math_block docname="Flocculation/Floc_Design_Concepts" ids="equation-s-of-kheq" label="S_of_KHeQ" nowrap="False" number="11" xml:space="preserve">S = \frac{Q}{W}\left( \frac{K}{2 H_e \nu G_{CS}^2} \right)^\frac{1}{3}</math_block>
            <line_block>
                <line>Where:</line>
                <line><math>W</math> = the width of the flocculation channel</line>
                <line><math>K</math> = pressure drop coefficient for the turn around a deflector = <problematic ids="id26" refid="id25">|K.FlocBaffle|</problematic></line>
                <line><math>\theta _e</math> = retention time in an expansion</line>
                <line><math>H_e</math> = length of jet expansion after a deflector, before the next contraction</line>
            </line_block>
            <target refid="heading-bibliografia"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="bibliografia heading-bibliografia" names="bibliografía bibliography heading_bibliografía">
            <title>Bibliography</title>
            <paragraph>Cleasby, J., 1984. Is velocity gradient a valid turbulent flocculation
                parameter? J. Environ. Eng. 110 (5), 875e897.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Swetland, K., Weber-Shirk, M., and Lion, L. (2014). ”Flocculation-Sedimentation
                Performance Model for Laminar-Flow Hydraulic Flocculation with Polyaluminum
                Chloride and Aluminum Sulfate Coagulants.” J. Environ. Eng., 140(3), 04014002.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Weber-Shirk, M. L., Lion, L. W., 2010. Flocculation model and collision
                potential for reactors with flows characterized by high peclet numbers. Water
                Res. 44 (18), 5180-5187.</paragraph>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
