<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.14 -->
<document source="C:\Users\cande\aide\aide_design_specs\doc_files\Flocculation\Floc_Purpose_and_Description.rst">
    <target refid="title-floc-proposito-y-descripcion"></target>
    <section ids="proposito-y-descripcion title-floc-proposito-y-descripcion" names="propósito\ y\ descripción purpose\ and\ description title_floc_propósito_y_descripción">
        <title>Purpose and Description</title>
        <paragraph>The flocculator causes particles suspended in the water to collide and agglomerate to form larger aggregates called flocs. The goal of the flocculation and sludge blanket processes is to minimize the concentration of inorganic and pathogenic particles that are not in flocs. Since there are two processes that help achieve this goal we can take advantage of the benefits of each process. In flocculation the deformation of the fluid makes that only particles of similar size can collide and agglomerate. Through the process of flocculation the concentration of first particles that have not joined to be flocs goes down. Therefore, the collision rate of the primary particles is also reduced and the efficiency rate of the flocculation process decreases.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>The process of collisions between particles and flocs in the sludge blanket is independent of the concentration of the first particles. Therefore the optimal design includes a rapid flocculation process and then the sludge blanket to efficiently continue the process of reducing the concentration of primary particles. Since it is not important to make large flocs and since the AguaClara hydraulic flocculator design has a relatively uniform energy dissipation rate compared to mechanical flocculators it is possible to make a flocculator with a high speed gradient. The high speed gradient also eliminates the problem of floc settling in conventional hydraulic flocculators.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>The flocculation process before the sludge blanket is key for two reasons. First, flocculation is very efficient in lowering concentration when and high turbidity peaks occur. Second, the water treatment plant has to work and be able to be started up without a sludge blanket. Therefore the hydraulic flocculator is key to the good performance of the AguaClara plant even though it is a fast process.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>In the hydraulic flocculation process, power is started with a difference in water level between upstream and downstream in the <problematic ids="id8" refid="id7">|HL.Floc|</problematic> flocculator. This potential energy is converted into kinetic energy at changes of direction and flow contractions. Then the water coming out of the contractions makes jets that lose their energy by swirling and the swirls become smaller and smaller. Finally the viscosity of the water slows down the small eddies but in the process the water is deformed. In the process of deformation the particles in the water are carried at different speeds by the water and in this transport by the water the particles can collide.</paragraph>
        <target refid="figure-turbid-water"></target>
        <figure align="center" ids="id1 figure-turbid-water" names="figure_turbid_water">
            <image candidates="{'*': 'Flocculation\\Images/turbid_water.png'}" uri="Flocculation\Images/turbid_water.png" width="150px"></image>
            <caption>The cloudy water in the bottle carries colloidal particles, which do not settle. The purpose of the flocculator and sludge blanket is to increase the size of the particles so that they can be removed from the water by the force of gravity.</caption>
        </figure>
        <target refid="figure-floc"></target>
        <figure align="center" ids="id2 figure-floc" names="figure_floc">
            <image candidates="{'*': 'Flocculation\\Images/flocs.png'}" uri="Flocculation\Images/flocs.png" width="400px"></image>
            <caption>The illuminated floccules at the end of a flocculator are already visible in size.</caption>
        </figure>
        <target refid="figure-floc-diagram"></target>
        <figure align="center" ids="id3 figure-floc-diagram" names="figure_floc_diagram">
            <image candidates="{'*': 'Flocculation\\Images/floc_diagram.png'}" uri="Flocculation\Images/floc_diagram.png" width="600px"></image>
            <caption>The formation of a floc through collisions between particles in the water. A floc actually carries thousands of the primary particles.</caption>
        </figure>
        <paragraph>In the AguaClara plant the flocculator is a series of channels with plates and pipes that direct the flow of water. When you go around a “deflector” or pass between two tubes, the water jet expands. This turbulent expansion is where conditions are created that promote collisions between particles causing relative velocities in the flow.</paragraph>
        <target refid="figure-floculator-isometric"></target>
        <figure align="center" ids="id4 figure-floculator-isometric" names="figure_floculator_isometric">
            <image candidates="{'*': 'Flocculation\\Images/floculator_isometric.png'}" uri="Flocculation\Images/floculator_isometric.png" width="600px"></image>
            <caption>Isometric view of an AguaClara flocculator with transparent walls. The blue arrows indicate the direction of water flow.</caption>
        </figure>
        <paragraph>The baffles are made of polycarbonate sheets. They are connected by a structure of PVC tubes made of <problematic ids="id10" refid="id9">|ND.FlocMod|</problematic>, with separators made of <problematic ids="id12" refid="id11">|ND.FlocSpacer|</problematic>. The flexible material is used so that the baffles fit precisely into the channels without gaps between the sheets and the walls. The modules are easy to remove for cleaning or maintenance of the flocculator (<number_reference internal="True" refid="figure-floc-deflectors" title="Fig. %s"><inline classes="std std-numref">Fig. 22</inline></number_reference>).</paragraph>
        <target refid="figure-floc-deflectors"></target>
        <figure align="center" ids="id5 figure-floc-deflectors" names="figure_floc_deflectors">
            <image candidates="{'*': 'Flocculation\\Images/floc_deflectors.png'}" uri="Flocculation\Images/floc_deflectors.png" width="450px"></image>
            <caption>The deflector modules of the flocculator.</caption>
        </figure>
        <paragraph>With the exception of the first channel, each flocculator channel has a <problematic ids="id14" refid="id13">|ND.FlocDrain|</problematic> diameter drain at the end attached to the plant’s cleaning channel. The drains are easily operated by removing a long PVC nipple that extends above the water (<number_reference internal="True" refid="figure-floc-elev-deflectors" title="Fig. %s"><inline classes="std std-numref">Fig. 23</inline></number_reference>).</paragraph>
        <target refid="figure-floc-elev-deflectors"></target>
        <figure align="center" ids="id6 figure-floc-elev-deflectors" names="figure_floc_elev_deflectors">
            <image candidates="{'*': 'Flocculation\\Images/floc_elev_deflectors.png'}" uri="Flocculation\Images/floc_elev_deflectors.png" width="600px"></image>
            <caption>Image of a flocculator with the deflector modules raised and supported by the cross tubes. This is done so that the low baffles are not damaged by static water pressure when the channels are being filled. The drain nipples are visible in the foreground.</caption>
        </figure>
    </section>
</document>
