<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.14 -->
<document source="C:\Users\cande\aide\aide_design_specs\doc_files\Chemical_Dosing\Dosing_Purpose_and_Description.rst">
    <target refid="title-dosing-proposito-y-descripcion"></target>
    <section ids="proposito-y-descripcion title-dosing-proposito-y-descripcion" names="propósito\ y\ descripción purpose\ and\ description title_dosing_propósito_y_descripción">
        <title>Purpose and Description</title>
        <paragraph>The coagulation and disinfection processes require the precise dosage of coagulant and calcium hypochlorite. To carry out these processes without pumps, the AguaClara plant uses a gravity dosing system.</paragraph>
        <target refid="heading-componentes-principales"></target>
        <section ids="componentes-principales heading-componentes-principales" names="componentes\ principales main\ components heading_componentes_principales">
            <title>Main components</title>
            <paragraph>The main components of the system are:</paragraph>
            <block_quote>
                <bullet_list bullet="-">
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Two tanks to store the stock solution of each chemical (four in total).</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>A platform to raise the tanks.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>Two constant load boats for each chemical (4 in total) that maintain a reservoir at a constant level using a float valve at the inlet.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>A balance that connects the water level in the plant’s entrance tank with the level at the chemical system outlet.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>A series of hoses in the path of the chemical from the constant charge canister to the balance, which provides the necessary relationship between the pressure drop and the flow rate of the chemical.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>One flow measurement column for each chemical.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                </bullet_list>
            </block_quote>
            <paragraph>The blue arrows indicate the path of the chemist. The height of the hose outlet on the slider controls the flow rate of the chemical.</paragraph>
            <target refid="figure-dosing-diagram"></target>
            <figure align="center" ids="id1 figure-dosing-diagram" names="figure_dosing_diagram">
                <image candidates="{'*': 'Chemical_Dosing\\Images/dosing_diagram.png'}" uri="Chemical_Dosing\Images/dosing_diagram.png" width="500px"></image>
                <caption>Diagram of an AguaClara dispenser mounted on the wall of the entrance tank.</caption>
            </figure>
            <target refid="heading-sistema-semi-automatico"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="sistema-semi-automatico heading-sistema-semi-automatico" names="sistema\ semi-automático semi-automatic\ system heading_sistema_semi-automático">
            <title>Semi-automatic system</title>
            <paragraph>This system has the following characteristics:</paragraph>
            <block_quote>
                <enumerated_list enumtype="arabic" prefix="" suffix=".">
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>The flow of the chemical is automatically stopped when there is no water flow in the plant.</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                    <list_item>
                        <paragraph>It changes the flow rate of the chemicals automatically in proportion to the water level in the entrance tank, which is proportional to the flow rate of the plant thanks to the linear flow meter (previous section).</paragraph>
                    </list_item>
                </enumerated_list>
            </block_quote>
            <paragraph>The first provides safety against overdose and chemical waste in the event that the flow of water in the plant is stopped without manually stopping the flow of chemical. The second allows an experienced operator to choose the chemical dosage easily, without making any calculations, and without having to manipulate the system every time the flow in the plant changes.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The system is not fully automatic because it requires an operator to choose the dose of each chemical and verify that that dose is being applied.</paragraph>
            <target refid="heading-bote-de-carga-constante"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="bote-de-carga-constante heading-bote-de-carga-constante" names="bote\ de\ carga\ constante constant\ load\ boat heading_bote_de_carga_constante">
            <title>Constant Load Boat</title>
            <paragraph>The constant load boat maintains a constant level of fluid that defines the starting height of the chemical’s journey. The level is maintained by a float valve at the bottle inlet.  With the canister the height of the start of the chemical’s journey is independent of the amount of chemical stored.</paragraph>
            <target refid="figure-load-can"></target>
            <figure align="center" ids="id2 figure-load-can" names="figure_load_can">
                <image candidates="{'*': 'Chemical_Dosing\\Images/load_can.png'}" uri="Chemical_Dosing\Images/load_can.png" width="500px"></image>
                <caption>Aluminum sulfate constant load pot.</caption>
            </figure>
            <target refid="heading-la-balanza"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="la-balanza heading-la-balanza" names="la\ balanza the\ balance heading_la_balanza">
            <title>The balance</title>
            <paragraph>With the constant loading boat defining the height of the start of the run and the pipes and hoses carrying the chemical permanently installed, the flow of the chemical depends only on the height of the end of the run. This end of the system is connected to a balance mounted on the wall of the inlet tank. On the other side of the balance is connected a submerged float in the entrance tank which tilts the balance depending on the water level in the tank (<number_reference internal="True" refid="figure-balance" title="Fig. %s"><inline classes="std std-numref">Fig. 13</inline></number_reference>), which depends on the water flow (<reference internal="True" refuri="../Entrance_Tank/LFOM#title-lfom"><inline classes="std std-ref">Linear Flow Orifice Meter (LFOM)</inline></reference>).</paragraph>
            <target refid="figure-balance"></target>
            <figure align="center" ids="id3 figure-balance" names="figure_balance">
                <image candidates="{'*': 'Chemical_Dosing\\Images/balance.png'}" uri="Chemical_Dosing\Images/balance.png" width="500px"></image>
                <caption>The balance is tilted depending on the water level in the entrance tank.</caption>
            </figure>
            <paragraph>The point where the hose that leads the chemical to the balance is mounted on the balance is a slider that can run along the balance. The dose of the chemical is chosen by manipulating the position of the slider, thus changing the height of the end of the run (<number_reference internal="True" refid="figure-final-height" title="Fig. %s"><inline classes="std std-numref">Fig. 14</inline></number_reference>).</paragraph>
            <target refid="figure-final-height"></target>
            <figure align="center" ids="id4 figure-final-height" names="figure_final_height">
                <image candidates="{'*': 'Chemical_Dosing\\Images/final_height.png'}" uri="Chemical_Dosing\Images/final_height.png" width="500px"></image>
                <caption>The final height of the chemical run can change because 1) the water flow in the plant changes or 2) the position of the slider is manipulated to change the dose.</caption>
            </figure>
            <paragraph>When there is no water flow in the plant the scale is level, so that the final height of the run is equal to the water level in the constant load boat. In this situation the chemical does not flow. When the flow in the plant increases, the float causes the balance to tilt further, lowering the height of the hose and increasing the flow of the chemical in proportion to the flow in the plant.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>To manipulate the coagulant dose, the operator changes the position of the slider on the scale. The lower this slider is placed on the inclined scale, the greater the flow rate of the chemical and the corresponding dose. In the highest possible position (marked as 0% in the numbering) the hose outlet is flush with the fluid in the constant load pot and the chemical does not flow regardless of the tilt of the balance. In the lowest possible position (marked as 100% in the numbering), the maximum dose (<problematic ids="id6" refid="id5">|C.CoagDoseMax|</problematic> of coagulant or <problematic ids="id8" refid="id7">|C.ChlorDoseMax|</problematic> of chlorine for this design) will be applied. Between these two extremes the relationship is linear, so that the percentage indicated by the number on the balance is the percentage of the maximum dose that is applied with the balance in that position.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>When the slider is reached on the balance, the chemical falls freely through a tube of ½”, thus isolating the path to the balance hydraulically. To allow the scale to move freely, this tube is connected to another large diameter flexible hose under the plant floor. This hose is connected to the pipe that carries the chemical to the injection point.</paragraph>
            <target refid="heading-small-hoses"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="mangueras-de-diametro-pequeno-elemento-principal-de-perdida-de-carga heading-small-hoses" names="mangueras\ de\ diámetro\ pequeño:\ elemento\ principal\ de\ pérdida\ de\ carga small\ diameter\ hoses:\ main\ element\ of\ pressure\ drop heading_small_hoses">
            <title>Small diameter hoses: main element of pressure drop</title>
            <paragraph>On the way from the constant load can to the balance, the chemical passes through a series of small diameter hoses in parallel. Almost all of the pressure drop along the path of the chemical occurs here. In this way, with the design of the hoses it is possible to control the relationship between the flow rate of the chemical and the height change of the path.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>The flow through the straight hoses makes the higher pressure drop dominate, and the lower losses (of expansions) are kept to a minimum. This is important because the proportioner has a linear relationship between the height of the chemical’s end of its journey (connected to the water level in the entrance tank) and the chemical’s flow rate. Higher loss systems with laminar flow provide this linear relationship while lower losses have a non-linear relationship with the flow rate.</paragraph>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
