<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.14 -->
<document source="C:\Users\cande\aide\aide_design_specs\doc_files\Chemical_Dosing\Dosing_Design_Algorithm.rst">
    <target refid="title-dosing-algoritmo-de-diseno"></target>
    <section ids="algoritmo-de-diseno title-dosing-algoritmo-de-diseno" names="algoritmo\ de\ diseño design\ algorithm title_dosing_algoritmo_de_diseño">
        <title>Design Algorithm</title>
        <target refid="heading-dosis-de-los-quimicos"></target>
        <section ids="dosis-de-los-quimicos heading-dosis-de-los-quimicos" names="dosis\ de\ los\ químicos dosage\ of\ the\ chemicals heading_dosis_de_los_químicos">
            <title>Dosage of the chemicals</title>
            <paragraph>The dispenser is designed for the doses detailed in the dimensioning tables below. The concentrations of the stock solutions are selected to be practical for mixing, low enough for the chemical to dissolve easily and high enough to last at least one day when doses are high. The maximum flow rate of the chemical should not cause significant head losses in the pipe leading to the scale, nor cause a loss of more than 30 cm at the float valve orifice of the constant load boat. Similarly, the volume of the storage containers is selected so that the chemical mixtures last a practical time given the stock concentration. The slab where the chemical storage barrels are located has an elevation of 31 cm measured from the top of the entrance tank wall so that the pressure drop at the float valve has no effect on the flow of the chemical. The outlets of the containers are raised 10 cm above the floor to leave room for the sediment to fall to the bottom.</paragraph>
            <target refid="heading-small-hoses-2"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="mangueras-de-diametro-pequeno-elemento-principal-de-perdida-de-carga heading-small-hoses-2" names="mangueras\ de\ diámetro\ pequeño:\ elemento\ principal\ de\ pérdida\ de\ carga small\ diameter\ hoses:\ main\ element\ of\ head\ loss heading_small_hoses_2">
            <title>Small diameter hoses: main element of head loss</title>
            <paragraph>Las mangueras de diámetro pequeño están diseñadas para proveer <problematic ids="id2" refid="id1">|HL.Cdc|</problematic> de pérdida de carga con el caudal máximo del químico. Se diseñan de tal manera que las pérdidas mayores (debidas a la fricción con las paredes de la manguera) dominen, y las pérdidas menores (debidas a expansiones y cambios de dirección en el flujo) sean mínimas. Este criterio limita el caudal que puede pasar por una sola manguera, ya que las pérdidas menores crecen más rápido que las mayores con aumentos en caudal. Para caudales en este rango, se selecciona un diámetro interno de <math>1/8</math>” por la facilidad de encontrar esas mangueras en mercados locales. Luego, el número de mangueras en paralelo (y así el caudal máximo en cada una) está basado en un porcentaje máximo de las pérdidas de carga total que se debe a pérdidas menores. Por fin, la longitud de las mangueras se define en base a la pérdida de carga máxima deseada de 30 cm, dado el caudal máximo en cada una.</paragraph>
            <target refid="heading-perdidas-de-carga"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="perdidas-de-carga heading-perdidas-de-carga" names="pérdidas\ de\ carga head\ loss heading_pérdidas_de_carga">
            <title>Head loss</title>
            <paragraph>There are two types of head loss that occur in the dosing system. The <emphasis>larger</emphasis> losses are due to the frictional force felt by the fluid on the pipe walls. The <emphasis>lower</emphasis> losses are due to the expansions of the fluid when there is a change in the geometry of its path. The design seeks to make the lower pressure losses negligible compared to the higher losses. This will ensure that there is a linear relationship between head loss and fluid flow.</paragraph>
            <paragraph>Head loss due to expansion is defined by</paragraph>
            <target refid="equation-head-loss-expansion"></target>
            <math_block docname="Chemical_Dosing/Dosing_Design_Algorithm" ids="equation-head-loss-expansion" label="head_loss_expansion" nowrap="False" number="1" xml:space="preserve">  h_e=\frac{K_eV^2}{2g}</math_block>
            <line_block>
                <line>Where</line>
                <line><math>K_e</math> = coefficient of expansion, which depends on the change of geometry</line>
                <line><math>V</math> = velocity of the fluid in the hose</line>
                <line><math>g</math> = acceleration due to gravity <math>\approx 9.81 \frac{m} {s^2}</math></line>
            </line_block>
            <paragraph>The head loss due to expansion increases with the square of the velocity, and therefore does not provide a linear relationship between flow rate and head loss. On the other hand, the head loss due to stresses with the pipe walls does have a linear relationship:</paragraph>
            <target refid="equation-head-loss-stress"></target>
            <math_block docname="Chemical_Dosing/Dosing_Design_Algorithm" ids="equation-head-loss-stress" label="head_loss_stress" nowrap="False" number="2" xml:space="preserve">  h_L=\frac{32\mu LV}{\rho g D^2}</math_block>
            <line_block>
                <line>Where</line>
                <line><math>\mu</math> = dynamic viscosity of the fluid</line>
                <line><math>L</math> = length of tube or hose</line>
                <line><math>\rho</math> = water density <math>\approx 1000 \frac{kg}{m^3}</math></line>
                <line><math>D</math> = inside diameter of pipe or hose</line>
            </line_block>
            <target refid="heading-diseno-de-las-mangueras-de-diametro-pequeno"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="diseno-de-las-mangueras-de-diametro-pequeno heading-diseno-de-las-mangueras-de-diametro-pequeno" names="diseño\ de\ las\ mangueras\ de\ diámetro\ pequeño small\ diameter\ hose\ design heading_diseño_de_las_mangueras_de_diámetro_pequeño">
            <title>Small diameter hose design</title>
            <paragraph>The maximum flow rate of the chemical in a single hose to control the error caused by the non-linearity of the minor losses is found with the following equation:</paragraph>
            <target refid="equation-max-flow-rate"></target>
            <math_block docname="Chemical_Dosing/Dosing_Design_Algorithm" ids="equation-max-flow-rate" label="max_flow_rate" nowrap="False" number="3" xml:space="preserve">  Q_{MaxManguera}=\frac{\pi D^2}{4}\sqrt{\frac{2h_Lg\mathrm{\Pi}_{Error}}{\sum K_e}}</math_block>
            <line_block>
                <line>Where</line>
                <line><math>h_L</math> = head loss in the dosing system</line>
                <line><math>{\Pi}_{Error}</math> = error due to non-linearity in the system <math>\approx</math> 0.1 - 0.2</line>
                <line><math>D</math> = inside diameter of the hose = 1/8”</line>
            </line_block>
            <paragraph>The maximum flow rate of the chemical that could be used is based on the maximum dose, the maximum flow rate of the plant, and the concentration of the stock solution. Dividing that flow rate by the maximum flow rate in one hose and rounding up gives the number of hoses running in parallel:</paragraph>
            <target refid="equation-parallel-hoses"></target>
            <math_block docname="Chemical_Dosing/Dosing_Design_Algorithm" ids="equation-parallel-hoses" label="parallel_hoses" nowrap="False" number="4" xml:space="preserve">  N_{Manguera}= \frac{Q_{MaxTotal}}{Q_{MaxQu\acute{i}mico}}</math_block>
            <paragraph>With the maximum flow expected in each hose, the length of each hose is with:</paragraph>
            <target refid="equation-hose-length"></target>
            <math_block docname="Chemical_Dosing/Dosing_Design_Algorithm" ids="equation-hose-length" label="hose_length" nowrap="False" number="5" xml:space="preserve">  L=\frac{\frac{h_Lg\pi D^4}{Q}-\sum K_e\frac{8Q}{\pi}}{128\nu}</math_block>
            <target refid="heading-valvula-flotadora"></target>
        </section>
        <section ids="valvula-flotadora heading-valvula-flotadora" names="válvula\ flotadora float\ valve heading_válvula_flotadora">
            <title>Float valve</title>
            <paragraph>The minimum float valve orifice diameter required to maintain the designed coagulant flow rate is given by:</paragraph>
            <target refid="equation-min-float-valve"></target>
            <math_block docname="Chemical_Dosing/Dosing_Design_Algorithm" ids="equation-min-float-valve" label="min_float_valve" nowrap="False" number="6" xml:space="preserve">  D_{OrMin}=\sqrt{\frac{4Q}{\pi\Pi_{VC}\sqrt{2g\Delta h}}}</math_block>
            <line_block>
                <line>Where</line>
                <line><math>Q</math> = flow rate of the chemical</line>
                <line><math>{\Pi}_{VC}</math> = coefficient of contracted vein for the orifice <math>\approx</math> 0.62</line>
                <line><math>\Delta h</math> = maximum head loss due to barrel height</line>
            </line_block>
        </section>
    </section>
</document>
