<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "+//IDN docutils.sourceforge.net//DTD Docutils Generic//EN//XML" "http://docutils.sourceforge.net/docs/ref/docutils.dtd">
<!-- Generated by Docutils 0.14 -->
<document source="C:\Users\cande\aide\aide_design_specs\doc_files\Mix\Mix_Purpose_and_Description.rst">
    <target refid="title-proposito-y-descripcion"></target>
    <section ids="proposito-y-descripcion title-proposito-y-descripcion" names="prop贸sito\ y\ descripci贸n purpose\ and\ description title_prop贸sito_y_descripci贸n">
        <title>Purpose and Description</title>
        <paragraph>After receiving the dose of coagulant, the water goes through the rapid mix. This process serves to distribute the coagulant evenly in the raw water. In this plant, the mixing occurs in the turbulent expansion of the flow that follows after an orifice in the pipe that leads the water from the entrance tank to the flocculator.</paragraph>
        <target refid="figure-mixture-diagram"></target>
        <figure align="center" ids="id1 figure-mixture-diagram" names="figure_mixture_diagram">
            <image candidates="{'*': 'Mix\\Images/mixture_diagram.png'}" uri="Mix\Images/mixture_diagram.png" width="400px"></image>
            <caption>The mixing of the chemical with the water occurs in the turbulent area that follows the orifice.</caption>
        </figure>
        <paragraph>The coagulant is injected through the wall of the tube just before the orifice. It is likely to be important to minimize the separation between the injection point and the mixture to maximize the efficiency of the coagulant. As the raw water contacts the pH of the solution drops and the coagulant begins to react with the other components of the water and form agglomerations on a microscopic scale. Distribution of the chemical must occur before the coagulation process is completed on that scale. Otherwise, an uneven distribution of coagulant in the suspended particles may result because the precipitated coagulant globules are added to each other before they get close to the particles. In this case a larger fraction of the particles are left without coagulant coverage and flocculation performance may suffer.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>Therefore, the coagulant injection tube is placed as close as possible to the fast mixing hole, and with the outlet in the center of the flow where the highest speed drags the chemical into the mixture as fast as possible (<number_reference internal="True" refid="figure-mixture-tube-exit" title="Fig. %s"><inline classes="std std-numref">Fig. 16</inline></number_reference>).</paragraph>
        <target refid="figure-mixture-tube-exit"></target>
        <figure align="center" ids="id2 figure-mixture-tube-exit" names="figure_mixture_tube_exit">
            <image candidates="{'*': 'Mix\\Images/mixture_tube_exit.png'}" uri="Mix\Images/mixture_tube_exit.png" width="300px"></image>
            <caption>The outlet of the rapid mixing tube at the flocculator inlet. The transparent plate with the orifice is held in position with the four PVC nipples that pass through the tube wall. The coagulant is injected in the center of the flow just before the orifice.</caption>
        </figure>
        <paragraph>The orifice is designed to produce a jet with a maximum energy dissipation rate of <problematic ids="id5" refid="id4">|ED.RapidMix|</problematic> at the maximum design flow rate. With this type of rapid mixing the energy dissipation rate varies with the flow rate. Also the minor scale of the mixture varies. The energy dissipation rate of <problematic ids="id7" refid="id6">|ED.RapidMix|</problematic> is conservative so that the mix also works with smaller flows.</paragraph>
        <paragraph>The jet of the rapid mixture exits in the space in the first part of the flocculator which serves as a contact chamber to finish the coagulation process. This part of the can</paragraph>
        <paragraph>al is considered as additional space because it is not included in the volume contributing to the flocculation in the design algorithm of that process (<reference internal="True" refuri="../Flocculation/Floc_Design_Algorithm#title-floc-algoritmo-de-diseno"><inline classes="std std-ref">Design Algorithm</inline></reference>). By providing this space for the coagulation process, no flocculator volume is wasted where the suspension must already be unstable for the flocculation to work.</paragraph>
        <target refid="figure-floc-entrance-tube"></target>
        <figure align="center" ids="id3 figure-floc-entrance-tube" names="figure_floc_entrance_tube">
            <image candidates="{'*': 'Mix\\Images/floc_entrance_tube.png'}" uri="Mix\Images/floc_entrance_tube.png" width="500px"></image>
            <caption>The rapid mixing hole in the flocculator inlet tube. The coagulant injection point should be just above the plate in the rapid mix tube, although it does not appear in this drawing.</caption>
        </figure>
    </section>
</document>
